Register of the Vitaliĭ Leonidovich Kataev papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Arms Control File, 1975-1999 (Boxes 5-11)
  - Conventional Forces in Europe (CFE) talks, 1987-1991
    - Charts of the level of armaments in the Warsaw Pact countries (Box-folder 8: 24)
    - Facts, "Conventional Forces in Europe,", 1988 November 25 (Box-folder 8: 25)
      Typescript, translated from English (distributed by NATO member countries at Vienna meeting).
    - Documents regarding CFE, START, and chemical and biological weapons, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 9: 1)
      Includes handwritten stenograms of talks made by V. Kataev.
    - Documents of the Soviet delegation for negotiations on CFE in Vienna, 1990 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
      Includes directions, suggestions, inquiries, information, data, and charts regarding different aspects of negotiations, as well as discussion on various issues regarding implementation of the agreement on conventional weapons in Europe, 1986-1992.
    - Speeches, negotiations on CFE
      - Ambassador Ralph Ekeus, head of the Swedish delegation, 1990 July 17 (Box-folder 9: 4)
      - Istvan Diarmati, head of the Hungarian delegation, 1990 July 26 (Box-folder 9: 5)
      - Ambassador of France, 1990 July 26 (Box-folder 9: 6)
      - Head of the Federal Republic of Germany delegation, 1990 August 9 (Box-folder 9: 7)
      - Géza Jeszenszky, Minister of Foreign Affairs of Hungary, 1990 August 9 (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - Summary of the talk between D. Manning, head of the political group in the British Embassy in the Soviet Union, and N. Izvekov, head of department, Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union, 1990 October 5 (Box-folder 9: 9)
    - "Conventional Arms Transfers and Transparency," paper for consideration at CSCE (Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe), Council of Foreign Ministers, Berlin, 1991 June 19-20 (Box-folder 9: 10)
    - Proposal introduced by the delegations of Hungary, Poland, and the United Kingdom on procedural approach to limitations on military manpower, 1991 July 4 (Box-folder 9: 11)
    - Proposal introduced by the delegation of Luxemburg on scope of manpower limitations, 1991 July 4 (Box-folder 9: 12)
    - Working paper from the delegations of Germany, France, United Kingdom, Hungary, the Netherlands, Poland, and Czech and Slovak Federal Republic regarding possible headings for a manpower/personnel agreement, Vienna, 1991 July 4 (Box-folder 9: 13)
    - Material sent to Kataev from Vienna regarding the questions reviewed by the joint consultation group on the CFE, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Chemical weapons talks, 1975-1994
    - 1975-1986
      - Speech of the representative of the Soviet Union A. A. Roshchin at the meeting of the Committee on Disarmament, 1975 June 24 (Box-folder 9: 15)
      - Kataev's notes from Geneva conference on disarmament, 1986 June (Box-folder 9: 16)
    - 1987
      - List of members of the interdepartmental working group on chemical weapons (Box-folder 9: 17)
      - List of unsolved questions in negotiations on prohibition of chemical weapons, Geneva (Box-folder 9: 18)
      - Directives to the Soviet delegation in negotiations on prohibition of chemical weapons, 1987 July 21 (Box-folder 9: 19)
        Includes memorandum of understanding between the USSR and the USA regarding bilateral agreement ensuring data exchange on stocks of chemical weapons and their production.
    - 1988
      - Illustrative table describing the time change in exchange of data between the USSR and the USA, 1988 January 1 (Box-folder 9: 20)
      - Directives to the Soviet delegation in negotiations on prohibition of chemical weapons, 1988 January 14 (Box-folder 9: 21)
      - Additional directives to the Soviet delegation, 1988 July 28 (Box-folder 9: 22)
      - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "Experiment in International Control over Non-Production of Chemical Weapons,", 1988 November 7 (Box-folder 9: 23)
    - 1989
      - List of unsolved questions in negotiations on chemical weapons (Box-folder 9: 24)
        Includes positions of the USSR and the USA on this matter.
      - Response from the CPSU Central Committee regarding accusations of Soviet Union involvement in expansion of chemical weapons, 1989 April (Box-folder 9: 25)
      - Additional directives to the Soviet delegation on negotiations on prohibition of chemical weapons, 1989 June 12 (Box-folder 9: 26)
      - Note to the CPSU Central Committee, "On Non-distribution of Soviet Chemical Weapons Abroad,", 1989 July 5 (Box-folder 9: 27)
      - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee regarding the results of the Paris conference on prohibition of chemical weapons, 1989 July 11 (Box-folder 9: 28)
      - Information for the members of the Politburo of the CPSU Central Committee on development of Soviet-American dialogue on the question of prohibition of chemical weapons, 1989 July 28 (Box-folder 9: 29)
      - Draft letter from Eduard Shevardnadze to James Baker on the question of the Soviet biological war program (for their meeting in Irkutsk, Siberia, 1990 August 1) (Box-folder 9: 30)
      - Response from Mikhail Gorbachev to George Bush on the question of prohibition of chemical weapons, 1989 November (Box-folder 9: 31)
      - Information on elaboration of a project in the state program of liquidation of chemical weapons, 1989 November (Box-folder 9: 32)
      - Note for the Politburo CPSU meeting, "About Measures on Execution by the Soviet Union of the Memorandum of Understanding between the USSR Government and the Government of the USA regarding Bilateral Experiment over Control and Data Exchange regarding Prohibition of Chemical Weapons,", 1989 December (Box-folder 9: 33)
      - Directives to the Soviet delegation for the Soviet-British expert meeting on questions of chemical weapons, 1989 December 6 (Box-folder 9: 34)
      - Question of prohibition of chemical weapons in Soviet-American relations (as of December 6, 1989) (Box-folder 9: 35)
    - 1990
      - Inquiry, prohibition of chemical weapons (Box-folder 9: 36)
      - Draft resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "About Directives to the Soviet Delegation for the Soviet-American Advisory Board on the Questions of Prohibition of Bacteriological and Toxin Armaments,", 1990 January 10 (Box-folder 9: 37)
      - Information on the cause of anthrax ("Siberian ulcer" - Sibirskaia iazva) in Sverdlovsk in spring 1979, 1990 January 11 (Box-folder 9: 38)
      - Notes from meeting with Jack Matlock and R. Breitweit, Ambassador of Great Britain to the Soviet Union, 1990 May 14 (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - Report to Mikhail Gorbachev regarding the question of chemical weapons, 1990 May 15 (Box-folder 10: 2)
      - Facts on the questions of negotiations on prohibition of chemical weapons (steps of the Soviet Union for the purpose of activation of negotiations), 1990 June (Box-folder 10: 3)
      - Official inquiry to Mikhail Gorbachev and Lev Zaikov from Mikhail Moiseev, commander of the general staff of the military forces of the Soviet Union, on the question of liquidation and non-production of chemical weapons, 1990 June (Box-folder 10: 4)
        Also signed by the members of the Politburo.
      - Material for bilateral negotiation on chemical weapons between the Soviet Union and the United States of America, 1990 June (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - 1991
      - Information, "Chemical Weapons," for meeting with James Baker, 1991 February (Box-folder 10: 6)
      - Order of Mikhail Gorbachev, "About the State Program of Liquidation of Chemical Armaments in the Soviet Union,", 1991 March (Box-folder 10: 7)
      - Material for the draft "Protocol of Inspections" and agreement of June 6, 1990 for study on the eighteenth round of the Soviet-American advisory board on prohibition of chemical weapons, 1991 March (Box-folder 10: 8)
      - Response to the President of the United States on the question of biological weapons, 1991 July 8 (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - Study, Nikolai Antonov (Major-General, Former Commander of the Military-Chemical Establishment in Shihany), "Chemical Weapons at the Turn of the Century," Moscow, printed copy, 1994 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Strategic arms control - confidence-building measures (CBMs), 1986-1999
    For related material, see Nuclear and space missile talks/Ballistic missile defense, space weapons
    - General
      - General material on confidence-building measures, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 10: 11)
      - Europe, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 10: 12)
      - Arms trade with Canada, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 13)
      - Reforming Soviet Union national security policy, 1986-1991 (Box-folder 10: 14-15)
      - Soviet-Chinese negotiations on elaboration of an agreement on leading principles of mutual reduction of military forces and enhancement of confidence on the Soviet-Chinese border, 1989-1991
        - General (Box-folder 10: 16)
        - Meetings of Soviet and Chinese diplomatic and military experts, 1990 June-September (Box-folder 10: 17)
        - Agreement between the government of the Soviet Union and the government of the People's Republic of China on mutual reduction of military forces and enhancement of confidence on the Soviet-Chinese border, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 18)
    - Proposals to the CPSU Central Committee on possible ways of dismissing accusations of breaking obligations on PRO and OSV-2 from the American counterpart (Box-folder 10: 19)
      Includes resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, 1987 April 20.
    - Records of main points of meeting with a group of American scientists and members of the joint Soviet-American non-government experiment on detection of nuclear weapons on the seabed, Yalta (Crimea, Ukraine), 1989 July 5 (Box-folder 10: 20)
    - Order from the Council of Ministers of the Soviet Union regarding the visit to American laboratories working on the problems of space armaments by a group of Soviet specialists, 1989 November (Box-folder 10: 21)
    - List of answers to the additional questions of the American side (from March 13, 1990) regarding data given by the Soviet side for memorandum of agreement (Box-folder 10: 22)
    - Memorandum from the group on realization of agreement for armament control, Embassy of the United States, Moscow, 1990 July 9 (Box-folder 10: 23)
      Includes referral to Kataev.
    - USSR/USA negotiations on radio navigation
      - Agreement between the US government and the government of the USSR on the establishment of joint Loran-C and Chaika radio navigation systems, 1999 April 28 (Box-folder 10: 24)
      - Summary of discussion of joint meetings of the USSR/USA representatives on the establishment of a joint USSR/USA radio navigation network and utilization of Chaika (USSR) and Loran-C (USA) systems, 1988 April 25-29 (Box-folder 10: 25)
  - Inspection issues, 1987-1991
    - General
      - List regarding strategic offensive weapons (USA) onsite inspection, undated (Box-folder 10: 26)
      - Additional arguments on the question of underground targets and their access by submarine-launched ballistic missiles (SLBM) (Box-folder 10: 27)
        Includes table of ocean squares used in notifications of submarine-launch ballistic missiles (SLBM).
      - Dimension criteria in implementation of a continuous onsite observation and inspection related to the intercontinental ballistic missiles (ICBM) or ballistic anti-submarine missiles (BASM), undated (Box-folder 10: 28)
      - Dimension criteria in implementation of continuous onsite observation and inspection of objects related to ICBM or Trident SLBM (Box-folder 10: 29)
      - Protocol of inspection regarding dimension criteria in implementation of continuous onsite observation of objects related to ICBM (Box-folder 10: 30)
      - Indication of free access to telemetrical information, undated (Box-folder 10: 31)
      - Resolution of the CPSU Central Committee regarding academician E. P. Velikhov's suggestion on attendance of the tenth state research-scientific testing ground of the Ministry of Defense of the Soviet Union in Sarshagan area by foreign scientists and journalists, 1987 February 12 (Box-folder 10: 32)
      - Data on visit to Votkinsk by a group of American congressmen, 1989 February 21 (Box-folder 10: 33)
      - Official letter from the CPSU Central Committee to G. Brown, American congressman, regarding Soviet anti-satellite defense laser, 1989 June (Box-folder 10: 34)
      - Analysis of the Commission of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs on the question of conducting continuous observation of missile production (according to agreement on reduction of strategic offensive weapons), 1990 May 14 (Box-folder 10: 35)
      - Data on organizing of inspection regarding the intermediate- and long-range cruise missiles treaty, 1990 July 11 (Box-folder 10: 36)
    - "Open Skies" Treaty (1990)
      Regime for the conduct of observation flights over the territories of states-parties to the treaty.
      - General, "open skies" information
        - General (Box-folder 10: 37)
          Includes main military-operative requirements for the realization of "open space" regime.
        - Research materials
          - Soviet initiatives regarding prevention of arms race in space and peaceful space research (Box-folder 10: 38)
          - Work of the Special Committee on the Conference of Disarmament on prevention of an arms race in space (Box-folder 10: 39)
            Includes working documents.
          - Development of position of the Soviet Union on the Conference of Disarmament regarding the question of prevention of an arms race in space (Box-folder 11: 1)
            Includes draft of order.
      - Basic provisions, NATO communiqué at the ministers level, 1989 December 14-15 (Box-folder 11: 2)
      - Basic provisions of a treaty on "open skies" procedures (Box-folder 11: 3)
        Includes terms and definitions.
      - Tables on the positions of counterparts (USSR/Warsaw Treaty Organizations-USA/NATO) on this issue (Box-folder 11: 4)
      - Draft of resolution of the Interstate Economic Committee on "open skies" procedures, prepared by the Central Scientific-research Institute of Radio Electron Systems, Moscow, 1991 November (Box-folder 11: 5)
        Includes supplementary material.
      - Report to Mikhail Gorbachev, "Instructions to the Soviet Delegation for the Third Round of Negotiations of Developing 'Open Skies' Procedures" (Box-folder 11: 6)
      - Results of the discussion of the "open skies" question by the Special Commission on Disarmament (Box-folder 11: 7)
      - Draft of response to the American counterpart (Box-folder 11: 8)
        Includes letter given by the American side in Houston regarding resumption of work on the "open skies" problem, 1990 December 11.
      - Negotiations on "open skies" issue
        - United States
          - Notes from meeting with Gregory Tillman, First Secretary of the Embassy of the United States in Soviet Union, 1990 January 3 (Box-folder 11: 9)
          - Notes of main points of meeting with J. House, chairman of American delegation to the international conference on "open skies,", 1990 July 19 (Box-folder 11: 10)
          - Notes from meeting with L. Sell, Adviser-Envoy of the US Embassy in Moscow, 1991 October 2 (Box-folder 11: 11)
        - Great Britain, notes from meeting with David Logan, Adviser-Envoy of the British Embassy in the Soviet Union, 1990 December 24 (Box-folder 11: 12)
        - Canada
          - Notes for meeting with F. Build, Deputy Minister of Foreign Affairs of Canada, 1989 June 16 (Box-folder 11: 13)
          - Reference material, "Open Skies: Task for the 90s," Department on Control of Armaments and Disarmament of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and International Trade of Canada, Ottawa, Ontario, 1989 September 15 (Box-folder 11: 14)
          - Notes from meeting with J. Breton, First Secretary of the Canadian Embassy in the Soviet Union, 1989 December 19 (Box-folder 11: 15)
          - Notes from meeting with G. Noble, Chairman of the Department of International Security and Control over Military Forces, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Canada, 1990 March 24 (Box-folder 11: 16)
          - Notes from meeting with M. P. Mediums, Adviser to the Embassy of Canada in the Soviet Union, 1991 January 9 and August 2 (Box-folder 11: 17)
        - Germany, notes from meeting with Norbert Baas, Adviser to the German Embassy in Moscow, 1991 July 30 (Box-folder 11: 18)
        - Hungary, notes from meetings with Hungarian officials, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 11: 19)
        - Draft of the elements of a communiqué regarding "open skies" issues, Budapest, 1990 February 5 (Box-folder 11: 20)
  - Non-proliferation regime material, 1987-1990
    - Soviet-American meetings on non-proliferation of missiles and missile technology, 1988 September - 1989 December (Box-folder 11: 21)
    - Non-proliferation of military missiles and missile technology (Box-folder 11: 22)
      Includes directions to the Soviet delegation for consultation with the United States of America, 1989 August 11.
    - Minutes of meeting with E. Verville, Deputy to the US Secretary of State, 1990 July 6 (Box-folder 11: 23)
    - Proliferation of missiles in third-world countries (Box-folder 11: 24)
    - Joint Soviet-American declaration on non-proliferation questions, adopted in Washington (Box-folder 11: 25)
    - Notes from meeting with J. Zimmermann, counsel on science and technology of the US Embassy in Moscow, 1987 April 14 (Box-folder 11: 26)
      Includes regime control over missile technology.
- Disarmament File, 1988-1997 (Boxes 11-12)
  Conversion projects, directives, drafts of resolutions, facts, statistics on general expense, and information on military budget and allocations required for financing measures in realization of agreement on reduction and limitation of strategic offensive weapons, arranged chronologically.
  - General (Box-folder 11: 27)
  - Geneva conference on disarmament, 1988 February (Box-folder 11: 28)
    Includes directives to the Soviet delegation, as well as a draft resolution on establishment of international system of control over non-militarization of outer space.
  - 1989
    - Statistics on general expense regarding execution of agreement on liquidation of intermediate- and long-range missiles in 1988 (Box-folder 11: 29)
      Includes tables.
    - Information from the Soviet Union KGB (Committee of the State Security) regarding evaluation of social-economic aspects of the process of disarmament (Box-folder 11: 30)
    - Military budget, data on general number of Soviet military personnel and armaments, information regarding defense construction (Box-folder 11: 31)
  - Allocations required for financing of measures in realization of agreement on reduction and limitation of strategic offensive weapons, 1990 (Box-folder 11: 32)
  - 1991
    - Information on expected reduction of defense allocations due to realization of the agreement on reduction of strategic offensive weapons (Box-folder 11: 33)
    - Tables depicting correlation of the military budgets of the USSR and the USA (1989-1990) (Box-folder 11: 34)
    - Soviet military budget for 1991 (Box-folder 11: 35)
  - Purchase allocation of armaments and military equipment in 1992 (in comparison with 1991) (Box-folder 11: 36)
  - Defense industry conversion, 1989-1998
    - General (Box-folder 11: 37)
      Includes lists, structure and trend of the enterprises participating in conversion production, facts, data, statistics, tables, and resolutions of the CPSU Central Committee and State Duma of the Russian Federation regarding conversion issues.
    - Conversion projects (Box-folder 11: 38-39)
    - Study of the Russian Institute on Strategic Research, "Conversion and Cooperation," Moscow, printed copy, 1993 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - Production of beryllium hard magnetic disk substrates, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Soviet Military Doctrine File, 1986-1992 (Boxes 12-14)
  Organization charts of the Party and Government Apparatus and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs; lists of members of Security Council, apparatus of the President of the Soviet Union, and members of the State Commission on Military-industrial Questions; proposals; suggestions; resolutions; studies; suggestions; and agendas and minutes of meetings on arms control decision making ("The Big Five"), arranged by topic.
  - General
    - Biographical data on executive officials and leaders of the defense industry (Box-folder 12: 3-4)
    - List of members of the State Commission on Military-industrial Questions, Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union, 1990 January 16 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Structure of the Party and Government Apparatus (Box-folder 12: 6)
      Includes lists of members of the CPSU Central Committee, Central Control Commission, and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1990.
    - Structure of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Soviet Union, undated (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - List of members of the Security Council of the Soviet Union and apparatus of the President of the Soviet Union, 1991 August (Box-folder 12: 8)
  - Status of the Soviet military doctrine (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Military balance, possible threats to the Soviet Union (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - Research on strategy development of the armaments and military equipment (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - Military-navy forces, undated (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - Military budget of the Soviet Union (1990-1992) (Box-folder 12: 13)
    Includes proposal of the CPSU Central Committee on widening open information regarding defense allocation, number of Soviet and Warsaw Treaty Organization military forces in comparison with military forces of the US, NATO, and Japan.
  - Suggestions on increasing work effectiveness of the military branches of industry (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - Draft resolution of the CPSU Central Committee, "On Improving the System of Planning and Management by Creation, Execution and Operation of Armaments and Military Equipment" (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Study, N. A. Brusnitsyn, "Control and Intelligence (Problems and Prospectives)" (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - Deficiency in conducting scientific research and experiment design work in military branches
    - General (Box-folder 12: 17)
    - Missile and space technology (Box-folder 12: 18)
    - Ministry of General Mechanical Engineering (Box-folder 12: 19)
    - Strategic missile warheads (Box-folder 12: 20)
    - Laser weapon in a system of anti-missile and anti-space defense (Box-folder 12: 21)
    - Missile and space production (Box-folder 12: 22)
    - Social problems, military industrial complex (voenno-promyshlennyi kompleks – VPK) (Box-folder 12: 23)
  - Commission of the CPSU Central Committee on questions of international politics, 1986-1988
    - Improving the organizational structure of the external economic organizations of ministries and departments of the Soviet Union (Box-folder 12: 24)
    - Information from the CPSU Central Committee regarding military cooperation with foreign countries (excluding socialist countries) (Box-folder 12: 25)
    - Military cooperation during twelfth five-year plan period with socialist and developing countries (Box-folder 12: 26)
    - List of armaments and military equipment supplied to Iraq (Box-folder 12: 27)
    - Information on joint enterprises of the Soviet Union and the members of the Council for Mutual Economic Assistance (Box-folder 12: 28)
    - Cooperation with European countries on space (Box-folder 12: 29)
      Includes main concepts of the joint program for a Mars study with the United States.
  - Military-technical cooperation with foreign countries
    - General, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 12: 30)
    - Warsaw Treaty Organization
      - General
        - Military doctrine, 1987 May 6 (Box-folder 12: 31)
        - Communiqué project of the meeting of the political advisory council, 1987 May 28-29 (Box-folder 12: 32)